Guide to the Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States, New York Commandery Records 1855-1920 MS 2996
New-York Historical Society
Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States, New York Commandery Records
1853-1920
1889-1913
New-York Historical Society
MS 2996
4.17 Linear feet
The records of the Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States consists primarily of routine correspondence to and from officers of the Legion. There are also a few interesting papers and artifacts from the Civil War.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged into the following three series: Series I, Correspondence; Series II, Financial Materials; Series III, Other materials.
Historical note
The Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States is a patriotic veterans organization that was formed in the wake of the assassination of Abraham Lincoln on April 15, 1865.
It was founded in Philadelphia, by three Union officers attending a mass meeting of veterans in that city to plan for participation in the funeral arrangements for the President. These three officers -- Brevet Lt. Col. Samuel Brown Wylie Mitchell, Lt. Col. Thomas Ellwood Zell, and Captain Peter Dirck Keyser -- wanted to form an organization that could help thwart future threats to the national government. Their model was the Society of the Cincinnati, established after the Revolutionary War. The name they chose, the Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States (MOLLUS), first appeared in a notice calling a meeting on May 31, 1865 at Independence Hall.
Other states soon formed their own MOLLUS commanderies, including the New York Commandery, which was instituted on January 17, 1866, with headquarters in New York City.
The organization originally consisted of three classes of members. Officers who fought in the US military during and after the American Civil War were known as the "Original Companions of the First Class." The eldest direct male lineal descendants of deceased Original Companions or deceased eligible officers could be admitted as "hereditary Companions of the First Class." Companions of the Second Class consists of descendants of living Original Companions or of living individuals eligible for First class membership. The third class was comprised of civilians who gave faithful and conspicuous service to the Union during the Civil War.
The organization still exists today, but now serves as a hereditary society (male descendants of eligible officers), rather than a functioning military order. Many Companions are nonetheless either military veterans or even on active military duty. Among other activities, Companions organize and participate in commemorative events, provide awards to deserving ROTC cadets, and assist with preservation efforts.
Organizationally, MOLLUS is composed of a National Commandery-in-Chief and individual state Commanderies. In 2016, there were 20 state Commanderies. States without their own Commandery are placed under the jurisdiction of an existing Commandery.
Since its inception, the MOLLUS membership has included nearly 12,000 Civil War officers. At its zenith, the organization counted practically every prominent officer among its ranks. Among them were Generals Ulysses S. Grant, William T. Sherman;Lt. Generals Philip H. Sheridan, Nelson A. Miles and John M. Schofield;Major General Winfield Scott Hancock, George B. McClellan, Rutherford B.Hayes, George Armstrong Custer, David McMurtrie Gregg and Grenville M. Dodge;Admiral David G. Farragut; Rear Admirals Bancroft Gherardi and George W.Melville. In addition to Ulysses S. Grant and Rutherford B. Hayes, Original Companions Chester A. Arthur, Benjamin Harrison and William McKinley served as Presidents of the United States.
Access restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to ten exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading Room for details.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Scope and Contents note
The Loyal Legion collection spans the period from 1861 to 1920 and contains correspondence, financial materials, membership records, and a few Civil War artifacts. The majority of the correspondence concerns routine matters such as memberhip, dues, in memoriam notices for deceased members, appointments, speakers, insignia orders, and similar types of internal issues.
Financial materials include account books, check books, and receipt books.
The collection also contains some interesting Civil War memorabilia, including a [blood-stained?] letter that passed across battle lines at Antietam, a piece of fabric from a Confederate spy balloon and a submarine cable used by the Confederates.
- Series I: Correspondence
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains correpondence to officers of the Loyal Legion. The majority of the correspondence concerns pedestrian matters such as dues, membership, nominations for office, speaking engagements, and the like. Some members corresponded using their business stationary, so the collections includes some interesting letterheads. There are also a few enclosures, such as programs, invitations, and pamphlets.
  Correspondence is arranged by recipient. Most letters were received by Legion Recorders A. Noel Blakeman (January 1907- May 1912) and William Cogswell (June 1912- September 1913).
  - Subseries I: Correspondence Received by the Commander, 1906-1912
    - Correspondence received by the Commander, 1906-1912 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Subseries II: Correspondence received by the Recorder, 1907-1913
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder, 1892, 1896, 1907 January-February (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1907 March-April (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1907 May-June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1907 July-August (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1907 September-October (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1907 November-December (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1908 January-August (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1908 September-October (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1908 November-December (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1909 January (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1909 February-March (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1909 April-May, September-October, December (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1910 January (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1910 February (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1910 March (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1910 April (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1910 May-June (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1910 July-August (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1911 January-October (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1911 November (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1911 December (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1912 January (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1912 February (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1912 March (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Blakeman), 1912 April-December (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Cogswell), 1912 January-May (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Cogswell), 1912 June-October (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Cogswell), 1912 November-December (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Cogswell), 1913 January-February (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Cogswell), 1913 March-April (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Cogswell), 1913 May-June (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Cogswell), 1913 July-September (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder (Cogswell), Undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
  - Subseries III: Correspondence received by the Registrar, 1909 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence received by the Registrar, 1909 March (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
  - Subseries IV: Correspondence received by the Treasurer, 1871-1913, undated (bulk 1906-1913)
    - Correspondence received by the Treasurer, 1871, Undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence received by the Treasurer, 1906-1908 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence received by the Treasurer, 1909 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence received by the Treasurer, 1910 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence received by the Treasurer, 1911-1912 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence received by the Treasurer, 1913 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
  - Subseries V: Correspondence received by the Chancellor, 1907-1913
    - Correspondence received by the Chancellor, 1907-1912 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence received by the Chancellor, 1913 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
  - Subseries VI: Correspondence received by the Secretary of the Nominating Committee, 1907 February
    - Correspondence received by the Secretary of the Nominating Committee, 1907 February (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
  - Subseries VII: Correspondence received by the Recorder-in-Chief, 1895, 1907-1913
    General Note
    These letters were received by the Recorder-in-Chief at the Commandery-in-Chief in Philadelphia, Pa. It is not known how these came into possession of the New York Commandery.
    - Correspondence received by the Recorder-in-Chief, 1895, 1907-1913 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
  - Subseries VIII: General correspondence received, 1895-1913
    - General correspondence received, 1895-1896 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents Note
      Includes letter from Francis Pinto enclosing a [blood-stained?] note passed between Confederate and Union lines fighting near the Dunker Church during the Battle of Antietam
    - General correspondence received, 1906 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 2)
    - General correspondence received, 1907 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3)
    - General correspondence received, 1908 March-December (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
      Includes program for unveiling ceremonies of the statue of General Philip Henry Sheridan in Washington, DC
    - General correspondence received, 1909 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
      includes invitation to Queensboro Bridge Celebration on illustrated letterhead
    - General correspondence received, 1910 January-July (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
      Includes invitation to opening Reception of the 25th Annual Exhibiton of the Architectural League on illustrated letterhead
    - General correspondence received, 1911 April-December (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
    - General correspondence received, 1912 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 8)
    - General correspondence received, 1913-1920, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 9)
  - Subseries IX: Correspondence sent (Letter books), 1877-1909
    - Correspondence sent (Letter book), 1877 May 11-1885 February 16 (Offsite-box 11, Volume BV Loyal Legion 1)
    - Correspondence sent (Letter book), 1887 April 12-1888 January 12 (Offsite-box 11, Volume BV Loyal Legion 2)
    - Correspondence sent (Letter book), 1888 January 18-July 26 (Offsite-box 11, Volume BV Loyal Legion 3)
    - Correspondence sent (Letter book), 1888 July 31-1889 October 12 (Offsite-box 11, Volume BV Loyal Legion 4)
    - Correspondence sent (Letter book), 1889 December 3-1896 September 1 (Offsite-box 11, Volume BV Loyal Legion 5)
    - Correspondence sent (Letter book), 1889 October 4-1890 July 7 (Offsite-box 11, Volume BV Loyal Legion 6)
    - Correspondence sent (Letter book), 1890 July 7-1891 June 29 (Offsite-box 11, Volume BV Loyal Legion 7)
    - Correspondence sent (Letter book), 1892 October 17-1894 May 3 (Offsite-box 12, Volume BV Loyal Legion 8)
    - Correspondence sent (Letter book), 1896 April 16-1897 December 6 (Offsite-box 12, Volume BV Loyal Legion 9)
    - Correspondence sent (Letter book), 1898 January 4-1899 November 28 (Offsite-box 12, Volume BV Loyal Legion 10)
    - Correspondence sent (Letter book), 1899 November 9-1901 January 6 (Offsite-box 12, Volume BV Loyal Legion 11)
    - Correspondence sent (Letter book), 1903 February 24-1904 December 13 (Offsite-box 12, Volume BV Loyal Legion 12)
    - Correspondence sent (Letter book), 1904 December 14-1906 October 3 (Offsite-box 13, Volume BV Loyal Legion 13)
    - Correspondence sent (Letter book), 1908 May 13-1909 March 28 (Offsite-box 13, Volume BV Loyal Legion 14)
- Series II: Financial Materials, 1890-1905
  This series contains account books, vouchers and receipts reflecting expenditures and income of the Loyal Legion.
  - Subseries I: Account books, 1892-1905
    - Transactions no. 7-192 (Account book), 1892 April-1905 December (Offsite-box 13, Volume BV Loyal Legion 15)
  - Subseries II: Checkbooks, 1892-1900
    - Check stubs 1-500 (Checkbook), 1892 January 21-1896 June 10 (Offsite-box 13, Volume BV Loyal Legion 16)
    - Check stubs 501-1000 (Checkbook), 1896 June 10-1900 August 14 (Offsite-box 13, Volume BV Loyal Legion 17)
  - Subseries III: Receipt books, 1891-1896
    - Resident dues, receipt stubs 501-996 (Receipt book), 1890 April 23-1891 December 2 (Offsite-box 13, Volume BV Loyal Legion 18)
    - Resident dues, receipt stubs 1101-1685 (Receipt book), 1891 Apr. 25-1892 May 12 (Offsite-box 13, Volume BV Loyal Legion 19)
    - Miscellaneous, receipt stubs 1100-1600 (Receipt book), 1890 September 11-1891 June 5 (Offsite-box 13, Volume BV Loyal Legion 20)
    - Miscellaneous, receipt stubs 1601-2042 (Receipt book), 1891 June-1896 December 22 (Offsite-box 13, Volume BV Loyal Legion 21)
  - Subseries IV: Loose receipts and vouchers, 1872- (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
    - Vouchers, circa 1872-1879 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
      Access Restrictions
      Restricted: These items are damaged and not available to general researchers
    - Vouchers, circa 1888-1896 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)
    - Quarterly returns and vouchers, circa 1888-1889 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
    - Vouchers and quaterly returns (undamaged examples) (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
    - Checks, 1913 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5)
    - Membership receipts (for initiation fees, duplicate badges, etc), #'s 78-2893, 1864-1883 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 6)
      Incomplete; not all membership receipts present
    - Membership receipts (for initiation fees, duplicate badges, etc), #'s 2894-3620, 1883-1885 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1)
    - Membership receipts (for initiation fees, duplicate badges, etc), #'s 3621-11860, 1885-1897 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3)
    - Membership receipts (for initiation fees, duplicate badges, etc), #'s 11914-12410, 1897-1898 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3)
    - Membership receipts (for initiation fees, duplicate badges, etc), #'s 12477-13062, 1899-1900 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 4)
    - Membership receipts (for initiation fees, duplicate badges, etc), #'s 13268-15219, 1901-1906 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 5)
- Series III: Other materials
  This series contains letters, maps, articles and papers that were recieved by the Loyal Legion. Notable items include a paper on the Elmira prison, a piece of fabric from a Rebel spy balloon, and a piece of a submarine cable.
  - Ballots, Candidates for Membership 1912 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 6)
  - By-laws and Articles; Report of Meeting (missing first page), 1865, 1897, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 8)
  - War Papers read before the Kansas Commandery; Kansas Comandery circulars, 1890's (Offsite-box 9, Folder 2-3)
    Paper topics include personal reminiscences of battles and commanders, the Nicaragua Canal, Lincoln, The Hospital Ship in the War with Spain, the Acting Signal Corps, the Campaign Against Wei-Hai-Hai
  - Civil war manuscripts and memorabilia, 1860's (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
    Related Archival Materials Note
    See also letter and note in Box 6, Folder 1
  - Wallet and documents belonging to Major H.G. Lockwood, 1853-1871, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5)
  - Description and photographs of a Confederate cemetery at Elmira, New York, 1906 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6)
  - Assorted evphemera, 1888, 1890, 1913, 1919 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 10)
    Includes printed material of the Loyal Legion, members' business cards, memorial notice, publication notices, and assorted other items
  - Date book (of unidentified attorney?), 1906 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 8)
  - Brass dies for Loyal Legion Library bookplates (Offsite-box 9, Folder 10)
  - Facsimile issued by "The Chicago Herald" on wallpaper of the July 2, 1863 issue of "The Daily Citizen" of Vicksburg, Miss. (Offsite-box 11, Box 10, Item 1)
  - Map of the Upper Potomac from McCoy's Ferry to Conrad's Ferry (inscribed "used in the last campaign of the Shenendoah Valley 1863-1864 with Major General Sheridan") (Offsite-box 11, Box 10, Item 2)
  - Photograph of the statue "Peace" erected on Monument Battlefield at Vicksburg by the State of Minnesota., 1907 (Offsite-box 11, Box 10, Item 3)
  - Notepad with shorthand, undated (Offsite-box 13, Volume BV Loyal Legion 22)